the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet will exam of
holography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of November 14th
1999. a little bit of the special and
different type of show this week what
I'm going to do is take a look back at
the last year in holography specifically
with the laser pointers and Laser diodes
and not so much go over it line by line
as far as what happened and when it
happened but I'd like to take all these
different elements that's happened
within the last year and put them
together into some sort of a way of
taking a new look at holography and how
we can do Holograms in new and exciting
ways with a completely new system
basically I I think once we finish with
this show you'll see that Holograms
really are being done or will be done in
a much different way and of course it's
still traditional ways as well we'll
continue years and years but
we'll take a look at some of the
advantages of doing them this way as
well
the big news that just came in earlier
today was from John clayer and John's
been working with the laser pointers and
and fiber optics and if you remember
from last year John was on the show and
he likes to go into caves and previously
he would take his helium neon laser and
put it in PVC plastic plumbing pipe and
with end caps and also take a six volt
motorcycle battery and crawl for maybe
what would be 45 minutes to an hour with
the motorcycle battery tied to his leg
the
helium neon laser of Throne over his
back and crawling through these caves
and have to set up all this stuff inside
the cathedral parts of the caves
themselves he was real happy to learn
about the laser pointer holography
because you could just put a laser
pointer in his pocket go down and do the
Cave thing but he's moved on to larger
power diodes now he's working with a 35
milliwatt and he said recently been
working with the fiber optics and you
know there's nothing new about doing the
Hologram of fiber optics I think I've
read several times in the past and it's
already been done but John has done
something there's very big news and
shows a lot of promise and I'm going to
get him on the show within the next week
or two when things have been completely
finalized but let me bring you up to
date on what it is that he's done
using two laser pointers and eventually
uh he wants to move on using this with
the larger power diodes as well he
combined two laser pointers and sent
them through ball lenses which you can
find like the Edmunds catalog just like
Marbles and I think John's even used
Marbles and essentially what that does
is when you take the laser pointer or
the laser diode and send it through one
of the ball lenses on the other side of
the ball lens you'll see a really bright
spot of laser light and that's where you
take your fiber optic and just press it
right up against the ball where that
spot is and the light travels through a
fiber optic well I did a very successful
single fiber hologram which you know I
believe has been done not within
necessarily with the laser pointer but
with the other lasers
but what he did this time is he took two
laser pointers now remember these fibers
are very thin they're they're hair thin
maybe a little bit larger than hair thin
in diameter and when you take two of
those or more and can bind them together
they become to the Hologram looking at
it a point source
it doesn't matter if you have one fiber
two fibers three fibers four fibers or
five fibers
it's still so small in fact five fibers
would be less than a millimeter in
diameter when they're all put together
and held together which is actually a
smaller point source than the exiting
laser beam of helium neon lasers which
is around a millimeter or your laser
diodes or laser pointers which is also
around a millimeter or so
so you've got a very small point source
and the Hologram plate holographic plate
sees this as a single point source of
light and it doesn't matter if you're
using a number of different diodes or
pointers to uh send your light to the
holographic plate so he made a very
successful hologram
using two laser pointers going through
two fibers having the fibers connected
together closely together and firing
just straight at the holographic plate
he says it's almost like a beautifully
spatially filtered light going to uh the
holographic plate unlike what goes
through lenses and things of that nature
now what's going to be exciting about
this
and we're going to find out about this
as time goes on it was successful with
two can it be successful with four or
five and if it can can it be successful
with the higher power diage can you
imagine having 35 milliwatt diodes uh
five of them all being pumped into fiber
optics and then having all those fibers
all Compact and nice and nice and
tightly together providing the
illumination for your single beam
hologram and John Claire has
verified that the power is increased by
using the two pointers he shut one of
them off and took his reading then
turned the other one on so they had two
of them on and took another reading with
his uh with his photometer system that
he's got set up down there and said that
he did see that the two Powers were
combined
in brightness so would it be possible to
put five 35 milliwatt diodes together
feed them into fiber have those fiber
strands all packed tightly together into
one little point source and wind up with
about 100 milliwatts or so of power
wouldn't that be absolutely incredible
this is really big news and I've I've
spoken to uh a few people trying to get
some input on this
and I've got a few varying different
explanations very similar to one laser
pointer holography started in diode
holography started there were just about
the same number of opinions as there
were people that you would ask why does
this now work when after years and years
people said that it could not be done
and I'm seeing the same thing with this
so we're going to have to take a closer
look at it and find out exactly why it
works the way it does and do all of
these beings as they're exiting out of
the individual fibers recombine into one
wave front traveling to the holographic
plate and creating the constructive and
destructive interference in the Emulsion
or
if you have five laser pointers or five
diodes are you essentially creating five
separate holograms on that holographic
plate but the fibers are so close
together and packed so tightly that when
you re-illuminate or play back the
Hologram you do not see five individual
Holograms because to the Hologram itself
they were so close together it just saw
the five individual sources as one point
source so there are a number of
questions that need to be asked but the
big news is that John clayer has created
a hologram using more than one laser
pointer I know Steve Michael and I had
spoken about this earlier in the year
and the possibility of using two laser
pointers but that was a little bit
different because we were taking a look
at split beam holography where one laser
pointer would provide the reference beam
and the other laser pointer would
provide the object beam so this is
something a little bit different than
what Steve and I were talking about and
trying to work out earlier in the year
but it fits in very nicely with this
show because what we're going to do is
take another look at single beam
holography and it's re-emergence as a
very viable way of doing Holograms
especially with the diode lasers right
now so what I did is I wrote down a
number of different things excuse me
that I'd like to cover with you and sort
of put together the
different advances that have happened
within the last year using diodes to
create Holograms along with a few other
things as well and what emerges from all
these individual things is a completely
new way of looking at Holograms and
doing holography in the first place
of course we start off with our diodes
themselves and the diodes are definitely
a cause of quite a bit of excitement in
the holographic Community originally
just with the amateurs and hobbyists but
now several professional holographers
seem very excited about this development
as well so we are starting to see quite
a bit of excitement and move away from
your traditional gas lasers to the diode
lasers themselves and not surprisingly
since a relatively high power I mean
we're not looking into the watts of
power here but we are looking into
compared to the helium neon laser some
higher power such as 35 milliwatts and
the possibility of getting a hold of
these new 50 milliwatt diodes when
they're out and at low cost at low cost
they're small don't drop one of the raw
diodes on the floor because you're going
to be down on your hands and knees
looking for them you can't you can't see
them you know and and portable even the
modules themselves with the battery
power supplies
that you can build for them you can put
them right in your shirt pocket at 35
milliwatts
so that's that's one thing that we're
all fairly aware of already
and also we want to talk about I'd like
to mention the recording materials that
are available both in both the HRT
recording materials and slab recording
materials that are showing a very high
diffraction efficiency especially with
single Beam work which traditionally
with the older AG from materials gave I
don't know so-so results there's been
some very nice single beam Holograms
created using AG from materials but
nothing compared to the brightness and
Clarity and snap of the single Beam work
that the newer materials with their
higher diffraction efficiencies can
provide
and not to mention making your own
holographic plates that was a
development that was just reported on
this show two weeks ago uh by Jeff
Blythe who had sent some materials to me
that was published in one of the
journals and for your information this
week and I still receive emails
requesting this information this hasn't
died down yet by any stretch of the
imagination with these major and
holographic plates on the holotalk page
you will find a link to those materials
once again both the published paper and
also the worksheet on how it's done so
on the whole talk page I've got that
back up for you because I've received
several emails about where can I find
this blah blah blah it's up there for
you now so take advantage of that
download that and go over those
materials and who knows you can make
your own holographic plates
there's also some several new processing
techniques I got a call on Friday from
Hans belkhagen and I believe he's going
to come on the show and talk to us about
the different processing techniques to
use with both the HRT and slavage
materials to really give High
diffraction efficiencies even Beyond
some of the
efficiencies that we've got currently
using the processing schemes that we've
recorded in the past such as the
pyrochrome process and whatnot so that's
going to be interesting to see now where
does this where does this take us we've
got three things here we've got
inexpensive diodes
we've got the um
they exceed the performance of the
helium neon laser with their stability
and the coherence length so we've got a
a source that's brand new that's working
better than any other Source before and
we've got the new recording materials
and we've got new processing techniques
well this puts us in the position to do
so much more with single Beam work and
why single beam well then here's a
couple reasons
let's take a quick visit to split being
land everyone always wanted to do split
beam Holograms and also the H1 H2
transfers where you do your laser
transmission master and then you do your
reflection copy from that H1 master
one of the main reasons for doing that
in the first place
was due to the fact that the earlier
recording materials did not display a
very high diffraction efficiency in the
first place and you had the ability to
adjust your beam ratios and get them to
the point where you could really dial in
about the brightest hologram that you
could get by using either variable beam
splitter or having several Bean
Splitters like your 50 50s 40 20s I mean
40 60s 30s 70s and so on and so forth
that you couldn't afford one of those
big variable beam Splitters but with the
new recording materials
some of the single beam Holograms that
I've done on the new materials are
brighter than any of the H1 H2 transfers
that I've done with the helium neon
laser
so what is the point some people say
well
I can illuminate my master subject
better with a split beam setup I can
control the illumination light a lot
better well that may be true and it may
not but I'd also like to point you to a
web page
by Vidar
hegdal I'm sorry and Ronnie Anderson of
Norway they have the holography newly
page and on that page you will see some
really nice setups for doing single Beam
work where you can control
the illumination of the object
yes that's true you can control the
illumination of your object and even get
extra illumination still doing single
Beam work and you'll find a link for
that right on the whole talk page so you
might want to take a look at that as
well
now here's one of the more exciting
things that's come out as you know and
as I've reported in the past and I've
also given a few cautions you can make
Holograms
with a laser diode module without the
collimating lens in there now here's why
I give this caution
in several instances
the laser diode assembly itself
I have to get a phone call because no
one's picking this up on a Sunday nights
hold on please
okay that's that's what I get for doing
a show on a Sunday night in any case you
have to be very careful when you do this
because in some laser diodes
they require the light reflected off of
that collimating lens back into the
diode assembly in order to control the
current
and if you remove that collimating lens
photodiode that reads that reflected
light no longer has that reflected light
to read and that's a very important part
of the entire circuit is to make sure
that that photodiode sees that light if
it's designed to do so now some laser
diodes you can do it with other ones if
you do it you will destroy them
thumb laser diode modules like the 35
milliwatt one that I have from Power
Technologies you cannot even adjust that
collimating lens
when that laser is at full power or you
will destroy the diode itself so you
have to be very careful with this you
have to know what laser diode you have
before you try because I know there's a
few Advocates out there of just taking
the
taking it out which works fine with some
of the laser pointers because a lot of
the laser pointers don't have the photo
diode feedback circuit in there in the
first place but if you've just gone out
and bought yourself one of the expensive
diode modules and you do that and you
burn it out you're going to be very
sorry you did it but
for the ones that can do this and the
later diode system and famine design you
can do this you do not need the
collimating Optics
okay the light that comes out of that
diode automatically spreads out spreads
fairly rapidly
but that's okay for single Beam work
you just adjust how far away you need to
have that diode from your plate in order
to cover it whether it's a four by five
inch plate an 8 by 10 inch plate or 30
by 40 centimeter plate you just continue
to move your diode back further and
further until you've got a nice clean
spread and it is a very nice clean
spread it looks like a perfectly
spatially filtered
red of white there is not a
there is no dust in it and there are no
Newton's Rings there's nothing in that
at all it's just a beautifully clean
spread of light coming right out of that
diode but once again make absolutely
certain that your laser will be able to
do that before you do it or you'll be
sorry that you did it
now what this boils down to is this
you do not need any Optics in the setup
all you need is your laser diode module
without the collimating lens and keep in
mind
if you're doing single Beam work you
don't need your four by eight foot
holography table anymore
because the only components that need to
be isolated from vibration are the
object and the plate
your laser does not have to be isolated
in part of that system your laser can be
just about anywhere you want to put it
and it will be fine as long as your
object and your plate is isolated from
vibration so what we can do
is we can build ourselves a little rig
and I'm going to do so over the next few
weeks because I'm going to start doing
my Holograms this way
build yourself a little rig that will be
adjustable
to hold either four by five eight by ten
or Thirty by five thirty by 40
centimeter Holograms and you can also
build it so that the light either comes
from above or it comes from Below
and you have wax inside there or you can
put your object on a rack you can put
your plate on another rack you can light
it in very creative types of lighting
according to the webpage you're going to
visit on the link there as well
and once you have that hologram
completed and you have it processed
you can put it back in the lack and
re-illuminate it with your laser light
once again
providing the Emulsion did not shrink so
you have to make sure you're processing
that technique is correct and you can
adjust the lack assembly inside of the
unit and put your copy plate so you can
do an H1 to H2 transfer
right in that rack and that rack is the
only thing that needs to be isolated
which means the only system that you
need to have isolated would be the size
of whatever the largest plate is that
you're going to do if the largest plate
that you're ever going to do is 30 by 40
centimeters that's how large your table
is going to be that's how large the rack
is and that's all you need to isolate is
that lack if the largest plate you ever
plan on doing is eight by ten then your
rack is going to be eight by ten and
that's the only thing it needs to be
isolated is that rack
so and your laser can be located
anywhere at all so basically you're
talking about just about a portable
completely portable holographic system
that doesn't require any Optics
and probably sit right on the front seat
of your car
with your laser in your pocket
and go anywhere you want to go and make
Holograms or make them anywhere you want
to around the house or in the basement
or whatever
so this is what's changed in holography
and let me just go down and tell you
what it is that I'm going to be doing
and you'll see how much different this
is in the traditional way of doing
holography I'm going to build my rack
system so that I can make Holograms up
to 30 by 40 centimeter and inside that
wax system I'm going to have it
adjustable so that if I have 8 by 10
plates I can change one of the racks and
it's eight by ten if I have four by five
inch plates I can check and change the
rack and it will be for four by five
inch plates I will be able to have it so
that I can hit it with the light that's
coming from above or light that's coming
from below I will not have to spatially
filter the light because I'm going to be
using the raw diode which is just going
to spread out and go onto the rack
I'm going to have a another rack in the
rack that will hold my object in place
and the plate will go above that I can
just put that right in the rack and have
that wait until it settles do my
exposure and process my plate and I can
then put that plate back in the rack
once again
and illuminate with the laser light
while I have another plate which is
maybe an inch two inches three inches or
however far away I determine it should
be and make an image plane transfer
all happening everything's happening
right in that little rack system and I
don't have a spatial filter I don't have
a lens all I have is just a little laser
that fires into that rack
and remember these are not going to be
very dim low quality home grams these
are going to be very high diffraction
efficiency Holograms you know go to
Lonnie and vidar's page and see the
beautiful images that they're making
although they are working on a table
there but you'll get the same type of
results with the rack providing that you
have the rack itself isolated from
vibration as well so there's no need for
the tables anymore in holography either
so we've got a number of different
things one that's happened in the last
year when all brought together
really does change holography because
picture this last year someone coming
along and saying
that you can have a 35 milliwatt laser
system that runs off of batteries and
fits into your shirt pocket doesn't
require any lens doesn't require any
spatial filter but yet you'll get a
beautifully spatial filter spatially
filtered beam coming out of it and you
don't need a holography table you just
need a little rack to do single beam
Holograms which are not the dim sink
single green Holograms that we're used
to they're very bright and image planed
single beams single beam Holograms that
are made with a little portable lock
system
think about that it's really changing
the way the holography is being done and
with this new discovery from John Claire
it's just getting more and more exciting
every minute you know if I'm there for a
while I was thinking well maybe we're
starting to reach the end of what it is
that we can do we know we can do lasers
laser diode holography now with higher
power diodes
maybe we've reached the end but lo and
behold I get a call from John last week
thing he was setting these experiments
up I spoke to him today
excuse me I need a drink of water here
hold on
I spoke to him today and he filled me in
on the experiments he did using the
multiple laser pointers and multiple
fibers
create that hologram that he created and
I'm really looking forward to see if we
can't work something out where we've got
like five of those diodes going and and
stacked at one time providing all that
illumination Powers Way Beyond anything
that's available at those wavelengths
traditionally
even the spectrophysics 125b is a 50
milliwatt laser and if you've got a good
tube in there and it's running pretty
good you'll maybe get 60 70 maybe 75
milliwatts out of it
but look at the price you're looking at
five figures for that used
here we are this is a very exciting time
I hope you enjoyed this show I hope I
didn't make things too confusing but I
really wanted to look back and see all
the different things that have happened
over in the last year because each of
these things happened sort of
individually
and I wanted to put them together into
one working system and just show
how all this has come together and given
us what could be considered a new way of
doing Holograms and holography in
general and I'm sure that as time goes
on this base
will be improved upon and we will notice
many many different types of holograms
that we will be able to get out of this
system so thanks for tuning in
I'll make sure to get John Claire on the
show in a week or two weeks when he's
got his experiments finalized
and I hope you tune in each and every
week
at some interesting guests coming up
and
my pleasure bringing you the information
if you have any emails about this
program I'm going to be out of town
Monday and Tuesday so if you can hold
your emails off until Wednesday I'd
appreciate it so my mailbox doesn't get
all clogged up thank you very much this
is Frankie phrase for whole talk see you
next week